So let's go to our colleague Abhishek Gupta
who has brought some interesting data.
Thank you Anjali.
If the elderly above 70 years of age are planning to take health insurance, then
they have the
option of Ayushman Bharat Yojana,
which is quite good and is a government scheme
which has also gained a lot of fame.  But
apart from that, there are many private banks,
sorry, private insurance companies,
which have in a way brought many health
insurances here.  So let
us know about them one by one
here.  So here you
can see that there are elderly people above 70 years of age.
If they want to take health insurance of Rs 10 lakh,
then which
company is
providing insurance here by paying the premium.  You can see that
Care Insurance Company charges an
annual premium of ₹49,842 here.
Next is Niva
Insurance Company which
charges an annual premium of ₹47,864.
After that there is Star.  Here, an
annual premium of ₹45.7 has to be paid.
If you talk about HDFC Aero here,
then here
you will have to pay a premium of ₹53917
and in the last is ICICI Lo LBA
in which you will have to pay a premium of ₹4610.
So in
case you go towards private companies, then
some of these options are available here, in
a way the premium is also
available on the chart here.  So you
can consider it here in a way.  Over
to you Anjali.  Absolutely,
Abhishek, you have explained in great detail how the
health insurance premium of Rs 10 lakh is
ultimately spent for an elderly person of 10-70 years.  So you are
seeing this on the screen also.  Let
us return to the guest once again.  Sir,
my next question will be as Abhishek was
also telling.  Is the claim process in Ayushman Yojana
completely cashless
or does the patient have to make the payment first?   Is
it
easier or more difficult than private insurance?  How will you
compare it, sir?
See Anjali, it is such that it is cashless
and whoever
is taking treatment has to
show his card only.  After this he does
not have to go to the hospital or the government.  He will get that discharge
treatment and will be discharged.   The
hospital has to file a claim.  Those who have
undergone treatment or
are insured card holders do not have any tension.   There
is no headache.
We absolutely.  Okay Sir, even before my next question,
I had said that there are many
elderly people who have the card but
they also complain that they are
not getting its benefits.
My next question related to this is that if there is an elderly person
who has got this card made
for the scheme but he is not able to get the benefit.
Even though he is eligible, Sir, where
should he complain?  Where should he appeal
regarding this?
See Anjali ji, I have already told you that there is
one medicine for all the problems. In this case, the
helpline number is 145. If you have
any problem
related to Ayushman Yojana, you can complain there
and your grievance gets redressed in a very short time. So,
if you are not able to avail the benefits of this scheme or are facing
any problem, then
you can go to the helpline number and register your complaint.
Sir, there are many
states which have their own health schemes.
If I mention Gujarat,
there too there is a similar card for senior citizens
where different
terms are mentioned.  So can the
state government scheme and Ayushman Bharat
scheme run simultaneously or is there any
overlap between them?
See, health is a state subject,
so it depends on the state's discussion whether they want to
run the Ayushman scheme in parallel
or not accept it all together, there are
some states which have not accepted it at all
and some states have
combined both, so it depends
on the state, it definitely depends on the state's specific state's discretion,
although everyone has different
terms and conditions
or the state governments already
tell and
disclose everything in advance.  I will get back to you sir.  Let's take
some questions.  The
questions from our viewers have come in.
Kamala Singh is from Jaipur.  His question has come.  Sir,
she is asking whether the elderly
can add both their husband and wife on the same card
?
Look, my answer to Kamla Singh ji is
that she will have to make only one card.  Now,
if both husband and wife are
senior citizens, then separate
cards will not be made for both of them.  A single card contains both
covers.   The
names of both will appear on the same card.
Absolutely.  So the next question is from Sir Vinod Sharma.
He is asking if I am from Delhi.  His
question was that if someone already has
private health insurance, will he
get the benefit of Ayushman Card?
Yes, why not?  You
can keep both insurances.  If you think
that the cost of my insurance will be
more than Rs 5 lakh, then along with Ayushman's Rs 5 lakh
insurance, you can
also buy insurance from a private insurance company.
And in this case you
can claim from both.  Cannot claim the same amount.
But for example, if you have an insurance of Rs 5 lakh,
then you can
do it from the insurance company or in Ayushman.
Suppose if it is for Rs 8 lakh, then you can claim Rs
5 lakh from one insurance company and the remaining Rs
3 lakh from another company. This is
exactly the question of Rajneesh Kumar from Patna.
Sir, although you have already answered it,
but once again his question has come, so
I will repeat it once again, is
mental health or
OPD treatment also included in this scheme? I will
say it again.  OPD
is not included and mental treatment is done only
if there is hospitalization.
Rest of the treatment will be OPD type treatment,
if it is for mental treatment then it will not be covered in it.
We absolutely agree and before this Sir,
you had also told that somehow
Ayushman Card is its own scheme in which
you can get the treatment done and
like other insurances, there is a
need to take separate riders.
Sir, there is no need to take any such riders in this.   It is
not a matter of necessity, you cannot take it
because this is a pre-scheme, so you do not have the
option of making any payment for free.
We
cannot take any rider.  Absolutely.
But Sir, is this Ayushman Card Scheme
sufficient for the elderly and senior citizens or should
they also take some private health
insurance separately?
As I told you earlier, the
cost of hospitalization has increased a lot.
Absolutely.  So, in this Ayushman Yojana,
only Rs 5 lakh is covered and
if both husband and wife are senior citizens, then both of them
together will be covered for Rs 5 lakh.  So for this,
if you can afford it, then you should
also have insurance of additional amount from
private companies.